this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
softball digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio hello this is Carol Padilla
for software engineering radio today's
episode is about the TOEFL framework for
Atheneum smart contracts and
decentralized app development with our
guest Tim Coulter Tim is the founder and
CEO of truffle the smart contract and
app development framework for etherion
Tim has been full stack developer before
joining consensus as a blockchain
developer where he created the framework
for aetherium welcome to software
engineering radio Tim thank you great to
be here truffle is known as the Swiss
Army knife for development on it here in
this episode we learned that that
statement also for the audience we've
covered blockchain and it helium as an
ecosystem in episodes 297 and 343
earlier but before we find out more
about truffle what is it helium for you
thing yeah so cerium is the next stage
in computer science in software
engineering if you look back at the
history of kind of milestones in where
software has come from you know what
computing has come from about every 20
years we have a new invention that
amplifies what we can do with computers
in this case it's a way of tracking
value on the internet digitally
I say value I mean anything that we
could give value to what this does and
how we have a system that can attract
value between people and interactions we
can actually open up doors
we never have before it suddenly you see
these borders you know like country
borders or something else interacting
with people you see them quickly fall
away so I'm kind of getting pretty deep
there but to me it's cerium is new
technology that's opening up you know
different ways of interacting with
people across the globe it's basically
have this global network in this global
computer and if there's a way to track
value on that computer that's more than
just a number in an account then you
didn't trade with them effectively
what if theory unless you do is it's not
straight-up counts it's not just numbers
in in an account you can actually script
those interactions create new ways of
interacting with people but the barrier
gets a lot lower as you could almost
raid directly with the person swimming
you are raiding inside an
internet-connected world gotcha so there
is definitely a lot of you know digital
exchange and digital native use cases
that seem you know more natural to the
etherium global computer quick question
that comes up then is how do we compare
this idiom to you know an existing a
world of web yeah so we've set up
systems that allow for those kind of
things but it comes a lot of friction so
if we go straight to the eBay example if
I wanted to sell something to somebody
else across the world using eBay eBay is
like a third party so I am relying on
eBay to provide a service for me and
that service is to make sure that my
transaction between me and this other
person actually goes through so we see
and they current like web 2.0 world is
we have these third-party services that
provide a lot of value but this puts
those companies at eventually at an
unfair advantage or potentially by using
those services to unlock this global
world puts us in harm's way for instance
let's say if eBay attacked or PayPal it
was part of that gets hacked and our
information gets taken from there or
something else or you know you've heard
all of these stories about people's bank
accounts getting frozen by PayPal and
and whatever else so what makes this
different is that in this case we've
built a system that doesn't need these
third parties the reason that aetherium
and blockchain technology in general is
revolutionary is because it provides a
systems of incentives for people to act
good people together it acts
instead of acting against each other and
so for instance in the eBay case you
might work with eBay to make a good
transaction a lot of the times that
might work out but at the same time you
might have somebody on the other end
that's trying to scam you well if we can
build the system one of the promises of
ethereum is if we can build an
internet-connected world of a blockchain
and connected world then we can
potentially have an internet that's much
better than the one we have that safer
and secure and you know causes us though
to be good actors so a lot of put points
around the eBay example compared to say
having third party Internet services you
know that accumulated all that unfair
advantage over time let's just deep dive
into the ATM stack rom a web developers
perspective think about a normal web app
I'm gonna go straight to like Ruby on
Rails does the easiest thing to do you
have some type of front-end some type of
back-end
you stick the back-end you know some
type of server on a VM somewhere connect
to the Internet and then serve the
front-end from there and that's that's
your application so when a user goes to
your website and interacts with your app
they're interacting with a front-end
code that then talks to the backend and
has a database and all that stuff
perform some service for you what
changes in the etherium world is really
the backend now there are advanced
aetherium applications that we can go
over at a later time but generally the
easiest way to think about that is to
replace the back end with the blockchain
now the blotching is a different
computing environment it's very
different from your server it does less
work than you can do on the backend
traditionally and you have to code in a
specific way to code for the blockchain
but what the blockchain provides you in
this case is you know that if a
transaction goes through and it's
processed it's processed everywhere and
because of you know fancy math and
cryptography you are guaranteed that the
results of that the execution of that
happened how they were expected to so
the very basic application you know has
a similar front-end in this case it's
just a bunch of static JavaScript and
HTML and CSS and then that talks to the
blockchain to get most of its data
that's a great way to put it you know as
looking at the blockchain architectural
II as the backend to all of these web
service
this that we're putting you on the front
end if I'm looking at it from an API or
a back-end a developer's perspective how
would you then define the layers from
the hidden box inside if you're no
normal backhand developer or the
blockchain you're no right some you know
Ruby code or something that's gonna be
the server it's gonna respond to
requests you're gonna use library that's
gonna make that easy for you in fact you
might even write your server application
to you know be restful and respond to
API requests or a typical applications
very straightforward from there but what
happens in the blotching world is you
know really completely different so you
are going to write some code that you
first need to compile call this this
code a contract it's a solidity contract
you're gonna take it and make a
transaction that puts that code on the
blockchain so remember this blockchain
is like this world computer it can't run
anything if there's no code on there so
you it's up to you to put it there and
once you put it there it's now able to
be called you can now call functions
that you wrote and then have it you know
run those functions in store data for
you the process of creating that code
and then deploying it to the lot chain
is a very different process than writing
the server software for instance and
just releasing a new a new version of
your server on a VM that you control if
you're building a very basic application
it almost makes some things completely
easier because you don't even have to
manage your infrastructure at that point
the blockchain again is a bunch of these
nodes running in synchrony so when you
build this application you put some code
on the blockchain that code has a
specific location and then you can tell
your front-end code where that location
is then once you do that all you have to
really worry about when you're like
actually deploying your application is
deploying the front-end that people use
and so it completely like changes the
game potentially and actually was to go
on a bit of a tangent what's really cool
about this whole thing
is that if you have if if you have these
systems of nodes we're talking thousands
of computers around the world running
this world computer and you no longer
have to worry about the backend well all
you have to really about it for uptime
if you're worried about uptime all you
have to really worry
is the front and there are even cooler
things coming out to complement the
processing that the blockchain does
effectively have you know blockchain for
storage imagine being able to deploy
your front-end on distributed storage
that's managed around thousands of nodes
across the world that front-end
interacts with the backend which is on
the etherion blockchain and suddenly you
have an application that can never go
down first off you have a login client
so some piece of software that that
connects to the etherium network and it
talks to the peer-to-peer network in a
certain way you have libraries that talk
to the clients themselves so for
instance that's web 3.0 and that's what
you'll mainly be interacting with in
your front end and elsewhere to make
transactions happen so I like to use
this human analogy and I like to talk
about it that way but it's such a deep
topic and it's like you really have to
think about the incentives that that the
users of the network have and of course
some people are incentivized to just
typically do good potentially that's an
easy way to say it other people are
incentivized to work in their best
interest I think if you're a protocol
developer you are building a gorilla
that makes people act in their own
self-interest but that self-interest is
aligned with the rest of the network and
so therefore you know everything works
out in the prospers
that's a gradient mataji comparing it
with you know human beings as part of
the the network of nodes where every
machine every computer is is as I said
earlier humming along in synchrony but
there's a there's a gain Theory aspect
to it and the protocol developer is
making sure that you know while you as
an individual are still you know somehow
as a human being acting in your
self-interest the common good is is
maintained and and we kind of
incentivize that amazing and definitely
a lot of yours right there's a lot of
depths to how that is achieved and done
so them going back on I our software
development lifecycle as all as we know
it from the web world if if I have to
like load
it's helium web-development what all are
the aspects in the helium stack that
that one touches and again not
necessarily you know one person would
know it all but how is that that stack
defined I think I think a large amount
of applications can be created with
within this stack will start very
bare-bones you have a smart contracts
that you need to write the most popular
language is solidity that's a language
created by the theorem foundation it was
created because writing smart contracts
is very different from writing normal
software to go on a tangent there for a
second literally every line of code
every bytecode of execution everything
that executed costs money costs gas in
the system therefore that that's a
completely different model of
development almost no developer in the
world is looking at their code in that
way where I need to reduce the lines of
code in order to write what in what I
means right but in a case you so you
start out with the language and that in
this case is solidity and then that
gives you gives you smart contracts now
do you need to get those contracts on to
the blockchain and then the blockchain
is gonna give you some data back to tell
you how to interact with those contracts
so the stack that most developers use in
its theorem right now is the truffle
framework trouble takes care of a lot of
this stuff for you so you write your
solidity code you deploy it to the
blockchain you get these artifacts which
are like the location of the code on the
blockchain what functions exist specific
data about that code for instance data
that you can use in debugging we call
all of that data artifacts we have these
artifacts those artifacts become your
core piece of information interacting
with the blockchain from anywhere else
so that is your basis that is your
back-end from here the front-end is up
to you and this is where a lot of things
differ so when you when I'm asked about
what's a default stack it really depends
on what kind of application users are
trying to build so you can take these
artifacts these basically the output of
truffle you can build a web application
in which case you could use any number
of frameworks the most basic library in
JavaScript for
interacting with the blockchain is web 3
whether ejs you could also use any
framework that we created cold drizzle
which is built to fit with react and
view j/s and a bunch of other front-end
frameworks in order to help you interact
at the blockchain without really having
to deal with all the the blockchain
details what i've been describing with
with these this is basically a web
application you can take these artifacts
and go a different route like you can
build a console application that
interacts to the blockchain you can
build a desktop application you can even
go further and build like you can take
the output on truffle and and build a
server application where you have your a
traditional web server that's standing
in front of communication with the
blockchain and manages that for users
I've kind of talked about this Global
Opportunities you have the traditional
stack is building a web application
there are a few steps and these are
steps that that I went through way back
when so it feels like such a long time
ago this is when it did like right
before a theorem was launched in April
of 2015 I was I was tackling the this
issue this exact thing like what needs
to happen and it's not it's not entirely
obvious so the the first thing you have
to do is figure out what type of
application you're going to build we're
just going to start there and why I even
mention that it's not even a link it's
not a tech related thing is because the
applications you build are very
different you're you're you could
potentially build a system where people
interact together and they're
incentivized to do certain things
typically that may not be that the type
of thing that you think about and so so
if you've got a good idea let's just for
example purposes go like you use a
generic token on the network and this
token make my trip might represent
something of value but let's say it's
tradable or something else and where you
start is first off you have to write the
smart contracts the smart contracts are
the you are literally describing the
interaction that other people are going
to have together and that might be
trading a token that my
the giving you know some tokens away
from it to another person but but
keeping other ones you might have like
you might have a more complex token that
like you burn some of it which is a
really interesting concept do for later
but after you you know write the
contract itself you compile it and
suddenly you're left with the bytecode
of that contract and now you're gonna
figure out what do I do what I do this
bytecode and so the compiler helps you
out but it's still like you don't have
anything on the blockchain yet so now
you have to deploy that to the ethereum
Network and deploying it is its own
thing of course you have to have a an
account that has ether on it and new so
you can run on the blockchain so you can
put that code on blockchain and then you
have to like make that transaction then
if you make that transaction and
everything up everything about that
transaction is good what happens after
that is the the blockchain goes okay you
did that right here's an address here's
where your code lives now you're still
not there you still don't have a
functioning application after you've you
put this code in the blockchain maybe
you create a way of you know knowing
what functions exist because if you
don't call the right function the
contracts just gonna be like it's going
to error basically so you have to record
you know what functions this and a bunch
of other information and then you can go
try to start writing the the front-end
of your application whether or not that
is a command line or a web application
or a desktop application where some code
at the front and so you start writing
the front end of view of your app and
that's where you interact with the
blockchain from a different side through
like Nagar it's a web app through this
plugin the meta mask plug-in perhaps and
you have to supply that that address of
that code is that the blockchain gave
you you have to supply that to the front
end so the front end knows well not only
what functions to call but like where to
call them like if you try to call a
function where code doesn't exist the
blockchain is just going to give you an
error back it's not your transaction is
not going to work
so you integrate that you know with your
front-end maybe you built yourself a
pipeline or something
to get the output of the compiled
- - what you're building and then you
know you go and you build it you're
you're testing things out and you know
finally once you finish you you might
have an application that works now the
thing is is that users don't have your
application yet so you need to take that
front-end at least and deploy that to
you know in some way that you can get it
in the web you would put it on a website
somewhere and then users would go to in
this case web users and go to your
website and run that code and they would
use their own connection to their
network and then now you have a full
deployed application that I I thought i
described all of that in that way
because figuring this out was was a mess
originally it was not something that was
easy for me to wrap my head around even
though I came from a web development
background there's a lot of I could
describe this in very different ways
that makes connections to you know
existing web development but but the
process is really there's a there's a
lot of steps to it and you could manage
that yourself or you could use truffle
the whole exercise I think the whole
experience you just mentioned about you
know starting from the the understanding
of a theme to writing your first part
contract you know compiling that you
know putting it on the blockchain you
know even before that you have to have
an account on a TDM to identify yourself
and like have that much value to make
that transaction happen it sounds like a
very new concept to anyone who's coming
from the web world trying to like
interact with a back-end server right
the the question is you mentioned a
little bit of like you know made a mouse
plug-in which is probably as you also
mentioned something about the the code
that the blockchain gives you and then
the address of the code can you just
elaborate a little bit on like what is
that code is it is more like an
interface or to an API like how do you
get that code yeah so in theory I'm we
call this the API that's actually output
by the compiler so one interesting thing
about etherion is it doesn't make that
information about what code is on the
blockchain it doesn't make that
available so and obviously that's that's
because it's a compiled language so you
can have 27 different languages that
compile down to this the EDM and they
don't necessarily have to have functions
like functions are an idea that helps us
as developers what is what it turns into
with the bytecode that you put on the
network turns into it's literally an if
statement so you you're setting a
transaction and the first this is all
kind of like abstracted out for you but
the first parameter is like what
function are you calling and literally
it's a it's just a series of bytes that
is unique compared to all the rest of
the other functions and the code that's
on the blockchain goes this is the code
that the compiled bytecode it has if
statements and that says is it this
function you're like is it is it this
identifier no is it this identifier is
this identifier and then it actually
goes and runs that so if it finds a
magic write it like jumps to the code
that represents that function and runs
it so it's super low level so you don't
have that you don't have that data
available to you which means that you
have to rely on the output of the
compiler and the compiler gives you that
information it tells you it gives you a
JavaScript object that tells you what is
there what's available for you and then
you use that in your workflow to
actually call that function later in
your front and one of the things that
you'll end up having to do if you don't
use a framework that provides us for you
is is you're not gonna want to be like
okay I'm going to call the function 0 x
AE four to seven because that's like the
the bytes of it right you're gonna want
to you you want to write code that
represents the code that you haven't
watching that's really like is to say
like my contract and dot send a token
right so there's like libraries and some
some layers on this run and to make that
experience a lot easier for you but but
if you don't use those you're gonna have
to figure that out
how would you then define truffle and I
do want to get into like two different
definitions back when you would you
would like you know coming up with this
vision what was truffle for you
yeah yeah I mean truffle literally came
out of a need to make my life easier at
the time so caiman came in the consensus
and figuring all this out there's all
these steps trying to wrap my head
around this whole stack like I needed to
build a whole application not just one
part of it I needed to build you know
from top to bottom so I can I can get an
understanding what this was and you know
it there were there all these steps in
it and ended up where I'm like well I'm
not gonna keep doing that by hand so I'm
gonna like write a script for that and
you know for instance let's say
compiling or something else and then
there's you know managing the artifacts
managing that well first off deployment
actually I was writing a script for
deployment then too
and then it's like okay well after
deployment I need to save some data that
I get so it's write something for that
and then I need to like pipeline that
data from that you know that comes from
the compiler and comes from deployment I
blend that to the front end somehow so
let's let's you know let's connect those
in a specific way so I built this first
project and then I moved to another one
as I finally got my gotta hang on things
and I would take those scripts that I
wrote from that previous project and
then light and transfer them over the
new on and then there'd always be a new
need so I'd like add to that and then
suddenly it just became this this thing
where it's like we'll shoot I mean I'm
getting I'm getting use out of these I
might as well package it up and give it
to somebody else and that's that's
that's how truffle was born so it came
out of need for my own development uses
with my own applications and then turned
into a framework that people use now it
is gone gotten so much well I'll say so
much better but be so much more advanced
so one of the things that the thing that
truffled those for you if I was to like
completely cut out all the you know no
pun intended
sweetness of truffle and just tell you
you like brass tacks what it does is
it's doing all of the like the the
gluing and it kind of like boring data
flow for you so you need to deploy
pursue the Union write contract and you
compile them you need to deploy you need
to debug
and you need to then manage all the
artifacts from all that stuff into the
front-end application you're building
and shuffle makes all of that really
easy so we we manage compilation it's so
weird because back you know you might
work with something like like visual
studio or something you press the like
build button and like all of your files
and code that you that you wrote is
naturally just compiled for you don't
worry about anything that's the
experience that exists and developers
are used to that did not exist for
cerium so like like you heard me like
sigh there for a second like we actually
perform network for you so in this case
all you have to do is worry about
writing your contracts and literally
just say compile and truffle will know
what to do a pilot for you save all the
artifacts and then we provide you a
system to deploy so again like this this
object-relational mapping like you want
to think about the contracts that you
create and and them having a place on
the network you don't want to deal with
all the nitty gritty like hexadecimal
code and stuff so we've provided a
system of deployment that allows you to
easily script your deployment steps that
system is heavily influenced from Ruby
on Rails where you have a migration
system so you're migrating the state of
the database from one from one step to
the next so you kind of that same idea
for a theorem anyway so it's at least
within the double world anyway so we
have these you can write deployment
scripts that are that are easy to use
and map back to the contracts that
you're writing easy to read then there's
actually what piece of this today that I
forgot to mention one thing that didn't
ever exist until trouble came along is
actual automated testing for foreign
contracts something you take for granted
like you move them over to a new
language you're like you expect certain
things to exist in that language and
suddenly you move over theorem and you
know three years ago you're like wait
where is everything so we take the the
same that same object facial mapping we
take
elaborate automated tests for it you not
only do me allow you to write tests that
you can run your tests against the real
blockchain but you know why do that
because the real blockchain is really
slow and it's going to cost you money
you can do it against a test blockchain
or like private blockchain so it's still
the same aetherium client but still
really slow you're still producing
blocks we've actually built development
blockchain this this this tech is
actually all throughout the products
that we built but it's in our main
product ganache but it's also in truffle
in this automated testing framework you
just write the tests and it'll run for
you as fast as possible you don't to
worry about the you know the slow block
times of the actual block chain so we
just got a new debugger this is
something that's the now lead developer
of truffle Nick D'Andrea wrote and
that's another thing that developers
take for granted and other program
environments like being able to debug
the code that they write well now you
can do that with aetherium so is your
building application where all the stuff
that trouble gives you we manage the
artifact process so we're you know what
bytecode your your code has where it
lives on the blockchain what functions
you can call the manage that process and
we give you ways to easily plug that in
your front-end again in a way that you
don't have to worry about the
nitty-gritty you have the object
relational model you're actually using
the same code on the front-end that you
use in your tests and in your deployment
scripts and you know we make that whole
experience better view well that's a
it's a lot of things that are made
easier for developers and throughout
that journey that you mentioned I would
just say like that the two steps that
you mentioned earlier like just compile
my smart contract get it deployed to the
blockchain and to the network get me the
address so I can actually die invoke
functions or I can write scripts against
our smart contract and do something with
it that itself would have been like you
know so difficult back then if you think
about not having a framework like Tuffle
yeah maybe should have described it this
way in the beginning but that's what
trap overrides is literally it gives you
the things that you're expecting from
a traditional development environment
but in this in this new web 3.0 world
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials in
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco / SC radio so Tim did you
look at any particular frameworks or
similar ecosystems that that inspired
your thinking about why you need to
create truffle and like how would you go
about doing it yeah so the four I'll
answer they're similar ecosystems first
I was building heavily building web 2.0
applications in Ruby on Rails so before
I started at consensus and so when I
needed to build something myself for the
etherium framework or seems me for the
etherium blockchain I pulled ideas
heavily from that for instance we have a
feature within truffle called migrations
which which is direct directly inspired
from Ruby on Rails and so that's where
in Ruby on Rails you would you're
maintaining a database over time and so
what you would do what would use these
migrations for is describe changes in in
the structure and format of data within
that database and you do that through
the migrations the idea being that
you're the this structure and format or
your database is migrating from one
state to another over the lifetime of
the application and I thought that when
I was building trouble I thought that
should be the same thing for truffle as
well so you're treating your contracts
or the etherium blockchain as the
database in this case is both the server
and and the database but at the very
application you could consider it to be
the database and so you might want to
treat your your contracts that you have
on chain in the same way so Ruby on
Rails was was a huge influence and then
from there as far as any any particular
framework I did look at an existing
framework at the time called embark
embark had some great things going for
it
but some of the design decisions and
choices that that embarked had built
were different from what I wanted so for
instance I wanted the code that that you
write for truffle in in always whether
or not excuse me not just for truffle
but but for your blotching application I
wanted that code to be the same
everywhere I wanted you to be able to
run run tests on not only a task block
chain but on your a real block chain at
least a real blocking client so for
instance the go etherium client you
weren't tethered to any any any
particular client and then there's some
other features in there it's actually as
I'm speaking now like I have to remember
all of these old decisions that were
made because since then truffle has
changed so much like we've added so many
more new features we're thinking much
bigger than we thought before so now
we're trying to pull inspiration from
from even other command-line tools for
instance our debugger is pulling some
inspiration from gdb can you also
highlight some of the challenges as you
were creating you know different as you
were thinking about different you know
features or aspects you know starting
with maybe the MVP of this you know and
then slowly you know getting to where
truffle became release ready yeah the
biggest challenge the the absolute
biggest challenge is knowing what's
gonna work so your job as a tools writer
is effectively telling users how to do
their job so inherent in the tool that
you're that you're creating is how to
use the tool and the how each step
though you know do this then do that
they do that and you know watching
application that how is is the hardest
part so in InDesign
the MVP and designing other features as
they came out you know we had asked the
question first off what would we do as
blockchain developers ourselves what do
we want what how do we manage our own
applications how do we want to manage
these applications as a team so from
there it's it's after kind of designing
that then it's asking or then it's then
it's actually figuring out the the
actual code like how are you going to
implement this and and there there are
some things that that help with that and
those are generally those higher-level
framework choices so for instance you
know as as I mentioned one thing that
guided the development was not being
attached to any particular chain
troubles not you can you can run your
tests and deploy against against any
etherium based blockchain or blocking
client whether or not that's that's the
etherium main net some private network
some offshoot of aetherium that's
aetherium based it's it's all up to you
so so we don't have any coupling for
instance in this example we don't have
any coupling to those chains great yeah
that's the talk process you know that
kind of leads you into you know many
different questions about traditional
way of coding you know managing apps
collaborating on source code all the way
up to deploying and testing and
debugging that code in a particular
environment sometimes you say that it
works on my local and then you take it
to define what does that mean
you know if you deploy to dev you know
test and then production if you were
introducing truffles to you know a new
application developer with some main
features some components and maybe an
early usage as a getting started how
would you introduce that if you're a
completely new developer and in your
getting started with truffle we would
likely introduce some some of the basic
same topics first so how the blockchain
works you know what does a transaction
how does how do you get code on the
network those those kind of higher level
things but
and this is actually a really hard thing
that we that we found over time so we've
done some trainings of truffle and tried
to just from the get-go you know we have
a people in the classroom from the
Gateway to tried to say okay here's the
blockchain and then and then use truffle
to to build with the blockchain and what
we found is people don't get it right
away
they don't actually make the connection
what you know why why am I using truffle
they don't understand the pain to put it
concisely they don't understand the pain
of not actually using it so what we had
to do in in one in one training
specifically is we had a pivot right in
the middle and say you know what let's
actually not use truffle at all and
let's go through the all of these steps
for deploying applications and building
applications in the lot chain and have
you have that experience first and once
they had that experience then they
notice that that truffle saved them so
much time and and so much effort so as
far as if I was selling
truffle to you or telling you what it
does the the first thing I would say is
is truffle at the at the very least it's
a pain reliever so it it makes your job
developing blushing applications easier
it makes the experience easier it makes
it a lot more fun
it makes the only thing that you have to
worry about being your blotch main
application developing testing and
debugging you're blocked in application
the contracts and the front-end
application that you're writing you
don't have to worry about the glue in
between how to manage data you know
between the front-end and the blockchain
you don't have to worry about how do you
talk to the blockchain we've got all of
that stuff covered for you but that's
just that's just the basics making it
easier we've added a lot of features
over time and one of the biggest ones
that I mentioned is one of our newest
features actually is the the debugger so
as I mentioned we got our we got our we
got some inspiration from gdb debugging
isn't something that you get
the blockchain by default when you're
debugging this is something you might
take for granted with with a different
programming environment where you can
write code and then just immediately run
that code stop the code in the middle of
it running and get a bunch of
information about it like that is that
is almost magical compared to what had
existed in in the blotching space when I
came on so we just recently released a
debugger this this tells you exactly
what's going on during a transaction it
tells you you know what part of the code
you're in it tells you the variables
that your contract is using it allows
you to look at those variables and look
at the the data that's stored there
gives you a ton of information on what
is actually happening under the hood so
that's huge
so you can technically debug a
transaction on any network now the way
that we've written the debugger is it
actually has the blockchain client
execute your transaction again but it
executes it in a way that it with it
with the same state that it would have
had during the when the transaction
actually took place and so what you're
doing when you're debugging we call it a
debugger you're actually looking over
the history of the transaction and this
history includes the state at every
point in time every byte code every
individual statement that gets run and
how it includes the the stack
information and the state of storage
basically all pieces of information on
the blockchain and you can this is a
history that you can you could actually
go forward and backward in time so the
trouble debugger doesn't yet allow you
to go backward but we are almost there
we will allow that in future feature you
install truffle and Pam install truffle
after you do that you know you now have
the truffle command line what you should
do from there just type truffle in it
this is this allows you to create a
bare-bones project now that's not any
scaffolding what we realized that that
will just give you the the the basic
truffle project
with the base of truffle config and then
the the folders that you're expected to
have but what we realized pretty early
on is that the applications people were
building with truffle are completely
different remember as I said before not
all applications are web apps not you
know you might be building a console
application you might be building
desktop application you may or may not
be using JavaScript at all actually for
your front-end so what you do next is
I'll say the world's your oyster here
now what we've done is we've made it a
lot easier to to tell users what to do
next but it's up to them to choose what
they what they want to build and then
we've also gotten ideas from the
community and all of this the comes in
the form of something called truffle
boxes so a truffle box is a boilerplate
application using specific libraries and
and tools that will work in conjunction
with truffle that you can get straight
from the command line so for instance
there's a box that works with react so
you want to create a react web app in
that case you just say truffle truffle
unbox react and it will go download that
project for you it'll download it for
you do the initial installation or any
other any other commands that need to be
run and all of a sudden you have a react
app that you can start building so if
you go to the the truffle box website we
have something like a handful of
official boxes so these are boxes
created by created and maintained by
truffle and then we have about 20 or
more community boxes that are maintained
by people in our community so for
instance we have one box our official
box which integrates truffle and drizzle
so drizzle is our own front-end library
that integrates very closely with the
output of truffle and so we have a box
that shows you how to connect the two
and that one is mostly focused on the
front end we have other more general
boxes so react you know I'm looking I to
the looking through the list now web
packs so that would be like like how do
you use truffle and create a
web application that uses react or web
application that uses web pack but we
don't just focus on those things so for
instance there's a there's a truffle box
called tutorial token and that one is
specifically focused on your contracts
how do you create an application that
has a token and this that this one uses
the open Zeppelin two opens up on
contract in order to show you how to
build those things it does include a
basic user interface but that just that
is that one's not meant to show the user
interface to you or that's not sorry
it's not meant to show you how to build
the user interface with trouble so we
have a we have a bunch more the
community is adding has added quite a
few of these boxes I'm scrolling through
now and it's it's more it's way more
than twenty but I would say that given
our that our community is is mostly
JavaScript or heavy JavaScript a lot of
these boxes are focused towards
JavaScript developers so first off
compilation so that is the easiest
command that one itself is just truffle
compile so if you if you type truffle
compile that will pull lead solidity
compiler that is distributed with
truffle itself and compile your
contracts immediately so from there
after compiling in the in the in the
general workflow of a blockchain
application after compiling and after
you've gotten the like on past any
compiler warnings or you think you're
ready to run that code all code all
contract code has to be deployed at the
blockchain before you can run it so this
this includes any even if you're working
on a test blockchain like a nosh you
still need to deploy it in order to to
get that coach run so the the next part
is migrations
again that's our deployment framework
that sets things up it's actually based
on or I should step back it's an it's
intended for you to deploy your
application to many different block
chains at the same time so for instance
you might be working on your local
blockchain ganach during development but
you might
also deployed you know the previous
version to the live network or the Rob
stand test Network and you have to
manage all of those deployments well
what if you were just writing your
scripts yourselves and being like you
might have to go through the process of
a thought process okay what script so I
what deployments Kurtz had to run in
that chain
what employment scripts I'd run on that
chain what the point scopes ever run on
that one and we decided that that was
too much of a burden we're working as a
team on watching applications so what we
decided and how we built this this
migration and deployment framework is
you actually write scripts but the
management of those scripts is actually
managed on chain so as you deploy it not
only puts your contracts and in your
contract code onto the blockchain itself
but it also says okay you have run
script number one the next time you
migrate there's no need to run that one
again and that's at least let's say you
did that to a test network like you
don't need to migrate script number one
on the test network anymore and of
course you can override this if you if
you know you're doing and you know
you've changed things around your course
or something but it manages your
migration State on chain so that all you
have to think about is moving forward so
that the future of your application and
Trevor will take care of maintaining
that future on these different chains as
you deploy them so both of the
compilation process and the migration
process output build artifacts when you
run either of those you will see this
output created in JSON files in your
build slash contracts directory and the
artifacts that get created there's
there's one file per contract file so if
you had a solidity file called my
contract Sol you would have my contract
JSON and that the JSON file includes
when you compile it includes a lot of
compilation output so this is gonna this
is going to be your bytecode this is
going to be there's actually two
different versions of the bytecode that
have to be stored depending on what
you're planning on doing with it so we
store both versions of that we store
other information so a whole abstract
syntax tree so for any tools
tools perhaps that want to analyze that
code that created the bike code we have
that abstract syntax tree we have
something called and we actually talked
about the before the ABI in order to
tell in in in our case in order to tell
drizzle and and JavaScript libraries
what functions they can they can call on
those contracts and we also store I
think we actually we may even store the
full source in there so there's one
source of truth because you might have
changed your source file after creating
that artifact well we saw a bunch of
information that's that's during
compilation and then during deployment
is when you actually put that code on
chain and once you put it on chain then
it actually has a location but as I
mentioned to you you might be deploying
your application on different block
chains and so these artifacts actually
store the contract address for each
chain that you deployed to so you might
have deployed you might have deployed to
the you know raphson test Network and
gotten one address well that address is
not going to be the same as the one on
main net so we have to we store that a
that network information there's an
identifier in there that is able to tell
truffle which network you're using and
then and then after that network
information it stores the address for
that contract does that mean that you
would also be able to actually index
these contracts somehow and then I can
actually search the the state changes
and maybe list them down over time we
don't have a state database yeah that's
a really good question actually this is
just we are just managing files on the
file system there are and and in in some
cases have been some timing issues so
imagine you deploy a version of your
contract on to the main net that has a
certain set of functions a certain API
and then you later go change that you go
change that API well now you what your
artifacts aren't going to at least for
the for that for them as far as the main
that is concerned your artifacts aren't
going to represent the same API that
actually exists on the blotchiness l so
one of the things we're working on is
something called truffle DB that's going
to maintain the state
changes over time and this will will
allow you as a user but also other
developers to see how these changes have
been made and be able to get the the the
state of that contract as it was
developed when it when it was deployed
for instance great that'll be a huge in
some sense you know to be good people
pretty simply although there's more to
it could be also like a good you know
version management of the contracts yeah
yeah actually so the way that you kind
of get past this timing issue is to use
something like get and be very diligent
about that version managing management
yourself but this will make that much
easier what's really interesting that I
guess the one thing that's that's
probably a lot different is the actual
address like you had this code not only
has this API but it also has a specific
location and that's a set of data that
that other development environments
don't really have to don't have to
maintain what is the config file that
you mentioned is it a JavaScript you
know file that I had to go and you know
I did two to create multiple targets or
is there a config file I can change yeah
so it used to be a JSON file so it used
to be just text that you would update
but it became pretty clear early on that
people wanted to do some more advanced
have more advanced configuration so
instead of us adding in every feature
that everybody asked for we instead made
it a JavaScript file and you can code in
your configuration to do what you wanted
it to as part of the initialization
process for truffle so this config file
now the biggest part of it does what you
suggested it's is how do you configure
multiple washings which block chains are
you pointing at and the this file has
evolved over time we're at a point now
where truffle has
100% good defaults for development so
you could not change that configure you
can have an empty configuration and
still develop and deploy on a test test
watching Network provided by truffle by
the way but but after you after you do
that after you've gotten used to how
truffle works then then you go into the
config and and say you want to deploy
the ganache to see what's happening or
you want to finally deploy to the test
networker or the main network that's
when you would go in and change that
there are other options there are other
more advanced configuration options that
exist there but the biggest thing is
just telling truffle where to point it
gotcha
and then if I want to do some some test
unit tests you know cover it as part of
my compile and deployment process what
what are features in truffle yeah so
well the easiest command is truffle test
that will run actually the behavior
there has changed recently so previously
you that you would have had to set up
your test network and actually have a
test network running yourself but as I
mentioned truffle now ships with a test
network built-in so you actually have to
you write tests and these are the it
uses the MOCA framework under the hood
what the test the test runner will do is
at the beginning of each test suite
which is a suite as is separated by a
file so beginning each suite it will
deploy your migrations or excuse me
deploy your contracts it'll run your
migrations but deploy your contracts do
the test network so that your tests are
starting from a state that you expect
and so these are effectively it's
setting up your test to run just like
your application would run after your
migrations are deployed on the main
chain you run truffle tests and then it
what it's going to do is it's gonna
after deploying your contracts it will
then run each test that you've specified
and it does it in such a way
especially if you're using the the
default test network that truffle shifts
with then it actually uses some extra
features we've added to that test
network that makes it super quick so it
deploys your contracts at the beginning
but it never has to do that again we
actually nap shot the state and revert
back to that state after each suite of
tests such wit we have done a lot of
work to get you the fastest running test
as possible so in in that you know if if
now like let's say we've done the
compile my creations we've also you know
done the testing as part of it you
mentioned that we use mocha J's
framework for the the test
what is the debugging like at this point
in time because you kind of mentioned
that the new features that you're adding
as a gdb like debugger so I think is
that the new state and how does how does
one invoke the debugging yeah so the the
debugger has been has been released
we're continuing to add new features to
it in order to get this debugger to work
first you need to make a transaction
that exists on chain now what that means
is that at the current moment
you can't debug any of those test
transactions that I mentioned to you
because the state is reverted on cleanup
so first you need to load a chain that
will actually allow you to get data from
it so there's a couple ways to do that
okay so you can load up your own block
chain like ganache which is a separate
program or you can use a private go a
theory network or for another watching
client or you can use a command within
truffle occult truffle develop truffle
ships with its own test blocking and
under the hood well trouble develop is
how you really access that in a way
where you can debug transactions so what
it does is it loads up a blockchain for
you makes that blockchain available I'll
get to that in a second and then gives
you a JavaScript console where you can
type commands in and these commands they
include all of the commands that you
could type on the truffle console so for
instance if you wanted to say truffle
compile in this console all you have to
do is type compile in that case and it
will recompile your contracts from
within that
but it allows you to write arbitrary
JavaScript and we make the JavaScript
objects for your contracts available to
you so you could actually play around
within this console and interact with
your contracts before you ever start
trying to write a front-end framework or
a front-end application that goes and
tries to connect with this chain to
finally answer your question what you do
is you can use truffle develop make a
transaction in there and then all you
have to do is type debug and then the
transaction hash and then you'll be able
to dive straight to the debugger what is
the kind of logging and like log access
for developers you know both as part of
debugging is but also you know later on
if I want to see you know what just
happened with executing a contract or if
I want to get behind the scenes of an
app like actually doing something over
my locally deployed watching the truffle
application or the truffle a
command-line tool does provide you some
logging so especially when you're in
when you're using truffle develop you
can use a special flag that will show
you the requests that come through and
the transactions that are made however
that might be enough for an experienced
developer if you if you need more than
that if you need more than the the
logging that's provided there I highly
recommend that you use ganache ganache
is a it is that same tech it is the same
it literally it's the same code that
provides you with the blockchain that
ships with truffle but in this case it's
attached to a desktop application that
shows you everything that's going in and
out of the blockchain so you not only do
you get that same logging about the
requests that are being processed but
you also get a view that you can explore
about what what accounts the the
blockchain is managing what transactions
are processed the blocks and and what
transactions are in each block and then
we have tons and tons and tons of
features planned with ganache it will
connect your travel project and then
give you way more information than that
so for instance you'll be able to click
through these transactions it'll tell
you the exact function that you called
for example if I'm a smart contract
developer and I want to bubble up some
logs is there any particular library or
method in truffle or even like web 3
events you know log so there's a
there's a flag for any command that you
run with truffle you can use the - -
verbose
- RPC flag and RPC in this case refers
to the the actual JSON RPC API that
truffle uses to talk to botton clients
and that will show you the very low
level requests and responses that that
truffle is using all that have thanks
for sharing that Drake one one thing
that you'll see is that truffle and the
tools that you use are highly correlated
when you're building an application the
tools are highly correlated to the
evolution of the actual application that
you're creating over time in this case
the application are those smart
contracts well people are building in
advanced ways of building smart
contracts that add features that the
blockchain itself doesn't provide for
instance upgrade abilities you can't
just if you want to have an upgradable
contract you don't get that out of the
gate if once you put code on the
blockchain you can you can no longer
change that code unless the code itself
allows for it so the details on
upgradable contracts get very complex
but what we're likely going to do in the
future is provide one or more different
upgrade ability options that are tightly
integrated with the the deployment
workflows that that truffle provides
here so how do I create over an app
development with with truffle with
something that is already deployed the
question is primarily towards you know
change management and pushing things to
prod
yeah so that's that's something that we
are currently working on now or I should
say we're we're heavily we're heavily
working on now
so to give you a bit of background but
start with an application that you are
creating let's say you haven't deployed
it anywhere what you'll do is you'll
first work on your local development
blockchain this is where you're gonna
make a lot of changes back and forth
until you are happy with those changes
so one of the reasons why you're gonna
wouldn't want to work on your local
development blockchain is because it's
super fast but after that you might
decide that the decision at after you
after you've gotten
the contracts to state where you're
ready to deploy the next decision is
really up to you
and up to your team if you're working on
a team and that decision is do I deploy
to a test network for instance like in
the Ruby on Rails world you might call
the staging do I deploy to a staging
environment where other people can use
those contracts and and interact with
them and so we can test that out first
there are levels of staging by the way
there's there's staging it may be you
set up a private network just for your
team that's you know fairly easy to do
or you can decide to use something like
the robson test network which is a
global test network you can decide to
deploy to that and then after you kind
of make that decision on whether or not
you go to staging from there you then
decide to go to the main network now
this lifecycle the the difference will
actually illuminate let me get really
detailed if you want to do that you will
have described these different networks
in your truffle config and these will
tell truffle how to connect to each one
but after that the steps that you need
to take in order to deploy Rx is super
easy
all you have to defer for the first one
you might say truffle deploy or truffle
migrate those are the exact same they're
an alias - - network and then say in
this case staging or you it really
depends on how you the exact name that
you use there for staging like in this
example staging that depends on what
you've act what you put you in your
truffle config but you might have an
entry in there for staging so you'd say
- Jeff Network staging and then you
might say - - Network maintenance but
where this gets you is this gives you
this have to get your contracts deployed
and then you can deploy your front end
application however you're going to
deploy that and now you have an
application that you can release to the
world this is where things get tough as
I mentioned before one of the properties
of the blockchain is that once you put
code on it you can't change it so
currently with truffle as it stands now
you have to code in your own application
lifecycle once you have deployed your
contracts
once and that could look very different
depending on what you want so for
instance you could you could build your
application in a way that has a very
like a dumb proxy contract that that
stands in front of your actual contracts
and you just update like where that
contract is pointing to that's one way
to do it that's a really easy way to do
it but you might also do more advanced
things where you have a contract that
gets requests or transactions coming in
and knows how to translate them to the
underlying code there's very complex
strategies you can use but the strategy
you choose is going to determine your
lifecycle here now the thing is is that
where trouble is currently failing is
telling users kind of how to do this
like what's the best way to do that to
kind of go back to you know as a tools
builder you are responsible for kind of
guiding users into how that how to do
their job or the best way or the easiest
way or perhaps the default and I think
one of our one of our major tenants is
like we will give you a good way to do
things and if you want to do something
more advanced or complex that's your
choice and you can choose to do that we
won't block you right but um we're
hitting a critical mass of developers
that that need these features that need
kind of guidance on how to manage this
change lifecycle once you've gotten to
version 1.0 so we are actively working
on that now you mentioned that a lot of
that you know maturity is coming in now
that the framework is getting battle
tested and and maybe more and more
applications that are going mainstream
are actually using and demanding that
that maturity are there examples where
you know you've seen some of the you
know teams that are out there reaching
out and like how do they engage you
today that's a great question so our
work exists in kind of two different
tracks one track is building up the
tools that developers expect to have
from all the existing environments so
for instance a debugger or package
manager right like we're working on that
at the same time we have another track
which is being reactive to the community
and build
the things that they asked for we're
building it in a new what you know web
3.0 way so in the past we've worked with
shape shift
they helped determine the features of
truffle for they were our big VIP user
in that case this time we're working
very heavily with colony for truffle 5
we do get a lot of feature requests on
github and from within our community for
instance from within the Gator chat but
what we what we generally do is find one
or two or perhaps a few via people we
call VIP users and then we we use them
to help inform the next version of the
tool we actually actually have a really
good relationship with colony we have a
slack channel a shared slack channel
with them one thing that we want to do
and I'm really glad I'm able to say this
here is that that we want to create
these VIP relationships with a lot more
people so people listen to this podcast
if you would like to have a close
relationship with the developers on
truffle and you think that you can help
guide the the next version we would love
to talk to you so like what and you were
definitely getting there into the
evolution of truffle and roadmaps you
are and thanks a lot for like actually
capturing some of the evolutionary
changes as we were discussing you know
the key features as we were discussing
the deep dives anything else on the
evolution you know since the beginning
that you'd like to highlight especially
also things that you would want to call
out on the roadmap so we talked about
the change management life cycle one
thing that that's really important to
that is deployments so I mentioned that
that we're going to be working on
upgrading that's not there yet but we
wanted to do some things with truffle
five that would kind of preempt that so
the thing is is that when you're
deploying especially when you're
deploying to the theory of maintenance
you are spending real money in some
cases hundreds of dollars depending on
how much code you're deploying if that
goes wrong and it could go wrong for
many different reasons for instance if
the if the network is under heavy load
but if that goes wrong you could be out
some of that
some of that money and the thing is is
that it's kind of like pressing the
button when you deploy to alive like
when you run your Ruby on Rails
migrations against a huge live database
you're like yes you spent a bunch of
time testing it and yes you you know ran
it on a staging server but you're still
finally you know once you wants you to
play alive you still have those those
butterflies in your stomach and you
going is it gonna work on the live
database and one thing that Ruby on
Rails gives you is that because you know
your database doesn't necessarily hold
the same properties that's blocking you
you can revert back but you can't you
can't necessarily you can't do that with
the block so you can't revert to
transaction so it's a it's a lot more
anxiety inducing and we are using
truffle 5 among all the many other
features we are spending a lot of time
to reduce that anxiety I've mentioned
ganache and ganache makes the makes
developing a blotching application a ton
easier and and basically it's what it
provides you is it is it it kind of
opens the black box that is the
blockchain so you might as a developer
you're giving you're going to have an
experience that it starts out you know
obviously you you're gonna try to have
that best experience with truffle you
might have you might use one of our one
of our truffle boxes that gets you an
application running you know from zero
zero to sixty in zero in no minutes flat
but it's but but that is still going to
involve a a certain amount of magic
you're gonna have your it's still gonna
take time for you to understand exactly
what's going on when on the some of the
basic stuff the basic block chain
development things like making a
transaction what does that mean or
understanding how how aetherium works in
a block
you know holds many transactions or
understanding what gas is for instance
well ganache tries to to open that up
for you and you can see exactly what's
happening in real time so III think I'd
mentioned we have a
of updates they're the the thing that
we're going to do immediately is
something called contract introspection
so that's what we're calling internally
anyway and contract introspection means
okay you have you are working with
ganache if you are working with ganache
how do we connect your truffle project
to take advantage of all of that juicy
information that's stored in those in
those truffle artifacts and then display
that to the user in a really nice way so
I kind of got to it a little bit before
I'm like okay we can tell we can tell
the user what functions were called we
can tell the user what what variables
were sent along with it we can show you
know if we go back to that idea that I
talked about of truffle DB if you you
know we have all those that artifact
information over time then we can show
users throughout their whole development
session we can show information about
all of those contracts even the ones
that have changed we can provide an
interface for interacting with the
storage of those contracts in a visual
way we can show events aventure events
are a special thing in solidity that
allows you to get information from the
blockchain in a special way so we can
have an event browser that gives that
information and finally we have a visual
debugger which is something that we we
can't wait to do and this will integrate
with the underlying debugging work that
we've done for truffle so that's that's
something that we have on the on the
list or ganache there's actually one
more feature that I really want to tease
out which is something that we're
working on one of the things that we can
do with ganache is actually have it
where during development you are
developing on the main network we've
built this technology already and all we
have to do is integrate it but with one
click you'll be able to develop with all
the code all the data and all the
accounts that exist on the main network
without having any of that information
actually make it back so for instance
you can deploy and make all the
transactions that you want without
having it cost you any real ether one I
haven't mentioned is drizzle the biggest
thing that
that I'd like to mention for drizzle
besides being what it is so drizzle is a
front-end framework meant to fit in with
react and redux actually not just react
its redux
it's redux eat but it can work with you
and other other front-end frameworks one
thing that we that we are really working
toward there is making the whole
experience easier for our users users so
not just for developers themselves but
the users who are going to access their
applications online the main feature
that I'm talking about is effectively
making the blockchain feel a lot less
like a blockchain and and what I mean by
that is when you run transactions you
generally have to you make a transaction
you approve it you wait 15 20 30 seconds
in order for that transaction to process
and then your application updates or the
application updates and then the user
can use it again well we're working this
feature called optimistic processing
that will run your transactions under
the hood in in a special blockchain that
that drizzle will provide you show the
state as if they ran on the main chain
and then you know wait for the the main
blockchain to catch up so it's uh
there's some experiments that I think we
need to go through in order to get this
right but if we do it right we could
drastically change our users experience
when when the user applications
definitely looking forward to you know
how some of those you know new
experiments and out and truffle fire
looks like you know something that you
know folks must try is to also call out
maybe the the mainstream catching up of
the you know the blockchain systems and
ecosystem and then how we can actually
make that end-to-end UX you know
development as well as the user
experience for the the end-user there's
a lot more smoother maybe seamless as
you mentioned about this this state
change that is happening and then
somehow we are able to still simulate
and predict that I think towards at
which the wrap-up like what's your guru
reference for all the things you know
blockchain decentralization specifically
even
tedium you know technology my go-to
reference every day is just the etherium
subreddit that has always been the place
that for me has had the the most
interesting news and up-to-date
information that subreddit has kind of
evolved into that that used to be like
the place in like 2015 when I say like
the I also mean like the only so that
that's evolved in a couple different sub
reddits now so there is death dev is a
big one that one you'll you'll find me
and other people
hang in there quite a bit that's a good
reference for new blotching developers
beyond those two I think that's mostly
it for me that's that's where I keep on
on most of my biggest news about what's
happening in the blockchain actually I
take that back
is that in crypto Twitter so crypto
Twitter is just regular Twitter but with
all the crypto people on it so I've kind
of established a bunch of cryptic people
to follow you can check out my followers
will followers list if you want that
might be a good use for people now if
you're if you're asking me where like
where you should go to learn about
aetherium or if you're if you're new or
you want to learn about how to program
for the blockchain the first place I'm
gonna say is check out troubles
tutorials for the etherium overview so
we have we have one focus solely on
aetherium itself it doesn't require you
know any anything about truffle and then
we have a petshop tutorial which that
one actually goes you goes through the
whole process of downloading installing
and using trouble for the first time so
those are those in the main yeah those
are the main things I would also if
you're looking for a solidity tutorial
itself this is where I go back to Lu
networks they're they're crypto zombies
set of tutorials is a really good piece
of information my go-to reference every
day is just the etherium subreddit that
has always been the place that for me
has had the the most interesting news
and up-to-date information that
subreddit has kind of evolved into that
that used to be like the place in like
2015 when i say like di also mean like
be only so that that's evolved in a
couple
subreddits now so there is s dev is a
big one that one you'll you'll find me
and other people hanging and they're
quite a bit that's a good reference for
noob watching developers beyond those
two I think that's mostly it for me
that's that's where I keep on on most of
my biggest news about what's happening
in the blockchain actually I take that
back
is that and crypto Twitter so crypto
Twitter is just regular Twitter but with
all the crypto people on it so I've kind
of established a bunch of cryptic people
to follow you can check out my followers
real followers list if you want that
might be a good use for people now if
you're if you're asking me where like
where you should go to learn about
aetherium
or if you're if you're new or you want
to learn about how to program for the
blockchain the first place I'm gonna say
is check out troubles tutorials for the
etherium overview so we have we have one
focus solely on a theory of itself it
doesn't require you know any anything
about truffle and then we have a petshop
tutorial which that one actually goes
you goes through the whole process of
downloading installing and using trouble
for the first time so those are those
the main yeah those are the main things
I would also if you're looking for a
solidity tutorial itself this is where
I'd go back to Lu networks they're
they're crypto zombies set of tutorials
is a really good piece of information
great I'll include these links thanks a
lot for many different be guilty
especially talking about you know your
experience in reference guides as well
as a new you know getting started with
it aging solidity and and truffle how do
you want to reach out to you yeah so me
specifically the best way is really
through email and this is you know
basically anybody on this on this list
is going to get the the direct access so
it's Tim at truffle sweet calm and
that's that's really the the most direct
way you know now in the in you know 2018
we have tons of different messaging men
ding applications the Gator channel used
to be the best way but now there's over
4,000 people there so it's hard to get a
hold of me directly there so email is
email is good for me
get her you can still see some of the
truffle devs there if you have a team
that wants to be in better contact with
us as just all of truffle developers we
can we could consider setting up a
shared slack channel which is super
helpful for us
and then there's if you have any like
business inquiries or anything else
there is a inquiry at truffle sweet calm
email address and then of course if you
have anything I think I'm required to
say this with a cantaloupe ever got you
know if you have any type of bugs or
feature requests please please PLEASE
direct those to the github The
Associated github repositories for the
library or application your you're
writing in about so for instance if it's
truffle you should go to github.com
slash truffle suite slash truffle great
Tim thanks a lot for spending you know
the time to deep dive on truffle and the
overall ecosystem with us this was
definitely very helpful you know lots of
things and hopefully you know in some
time we can look for you know what's
coming next with truffle 5 thanks
absolutely and thank you for having me
sure this was this is a great time I
really appreciated digitalocean is the
easiest cloud platform to deploy manage
and scale applications of any size
they're moving infrastructure friction
and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials and an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/se radio
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se Radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening